These are networks and networks have network effects,
meaning they get more valuable
the more nodes on the network.
And we're in a situation here with stablecoins
where 99% of the nodes that matter are highly regulated.
I mean, it's kind of remarkable
that we have trillions of dollars in monthly volume
where 99% of the participants of the network
feel like they can't join the network right now.
So the big unlock is one actual rules
that protect you from an FTX.
And then number two is now you've suddenly unlocked
this 99% of the world to join this network, right?
Here, the benefit is just so obvious
that I think it's gonna be clearly dominant.
(upbeat music)
- Welcome to Web3 with A16Z, I'm Robert Hackett.
Today we're taking a deep look at why stablecoins have emerged
as one of the most promising applications in crypto today
and how they could reshape everything
from international remittances to point of sale payments.
I'm joined by Chris Dixon, founder and managing partner
of A16Z Crypto, an author of the New York Times
best-selling book, Read, Write Own, and Sam Bronner,
a deal partner at A16Z Crypto
who focuses on stablecoins.
Together, we unpack the technical
and regulatory foundations of stablecoins,
we explore the cracks in the current payment system,
and we look ahead to what becomes possible
once digital dollars go mainstream.
We also dig into why the future of money
might end up looking a lot more like email
or the web than a bank.
As a reminder, none of the content should be taken
as tax, business, legal, or investment advice.
Please see A16Z.com/disclosures
for more important information,
including a link to a list of our investments.
- The internet has done a terrific job
in some respects removing intermediaries.
You could look at the way that the web
has challenged legacy media,
how the internet and connectivity
has kind of supercharged open source code,
getting around proprietary software.
What has taken so long for the internet
to challenge payments and finance?
And why is it stablecoins that have emerged
as a potentially compelling solution to this?
- The first and biggest answer
is that you need a global system of account.
You need a way for you to track where all this money is
until we have blockchains where we have credible,
trustless, global access to one ledger.
You're always gonna be giving your trust
to someone like Visa.
And so that system like did work,
but we had to rely on Visa in order to make it happen.
And then of course they got extracted.
That's what an extractive network is.
That's sort of a large part of the read-write on thesis.
What we see now is we have this capability,
but we still have a lot of problems
because the payments infrastructure was embedded
since 1970 and it had a long time to get pretty good.
So we need blockchains to get even better
and until about 18 months ago,
when L2s could process payment transactions
in less than one second and less than one cent,
until that happened crypto payments
just weren't as good as legacy payment rails.
But now they are and people are beginning to build
the connective tissue that'll actually allow it to compete
and be wherever users are today.
And so that's sort of the next phase
is how do we get to table stakes payments functionality
and sort of default on integration with the distribution,
with where people are today?
And so we're seeing that happen.
We're seeing people who wanna save money in U.S. dollars
in the global South,
people who wanna do international transfers
from countries that aren't well connected.
They're beginning to say,
hey, this is some hurdles still here.
The technology isn't perfect yet,
but already stable coins are beginning to meet my needs.
And then we're gonna expand the market
by building integration into apps people already use.
So my new bank app, my Venmo,
my card processor in a restaurant,
as we begin to light up those interfaces
and even larger segment of the market
is gonna come online.
But it all had to start with cost and speed competitiveness,
which is about 18 months old.
And so now we get this exciting
Cambridge explosion of opportunities as people take advantage
of that new capability.
- So let me just reframe it.
So the promise of stable coins, right?
What are stable coins?
They are blockchain-based systems
where you layer on dollars and other kind of quote-unquote
fiat money on top of these systems.
The simple way I've been explaining
like when I talked to non-tech folks,
for example, the policymakers,
the simple way I explain blockchains is
they're technologies that allow you
to build digital services that don't have intermediaries.
That's a little bit simplified,
but it directionally,
I think a very useful way to think of it.
So that what that means is you can,
if you do it right, build services
that function very similarly to how our payment system works,
but you don't have these companies
like Visa and payment processors and so forth.
In the middle, why is that important?
Because by putting it in the middle,
you're giving them power and that power lets them take money
and also lets them kind of wield control.
So sort of two dimensions, there's financial
and then kind of governance control.
The financial one, I think, is the easiest to focus on
because it's so visible and you can clearly improve that.
And it's significant, I mean, two and a half percent.
You know, we're in the tech world,
we're used to these 70% margin businesses.
Most of the world is much lower margin.
- And we did that analysis for grocery stores
where it's like a grocery store is making 2% profit.
We're talking about doubling profitability
of a grocery store.
There is this triple regressive tax going on here too
where the biggest retailers in the US
are negotiating custom rates
that are maybe 10 times cheaper, you know,
10% of the fee that your local grocery store pay,
Kroger's like paying much less than that.
And the wealthiest users get these rewards back.
And so in many ways, the average consumer
is really getting screwed by these extractive fees.
- This is truly scandalous and it's something
that people don't think enough about.
It's really the deck is stacked against the little guy
in this situation.
- It's true in all finance.
Like, you know, if you have a lot of money in savings,
you go and put them in treasury bills
and you get 4% and chase, you get 0%.
If you want to cash or paycheck, you know,
if you have money, it's effectively free.
And if you don't, you do pay a loan.
So like all of this stuff is highly regressive.
Okay, so there's the removing intermediaries.
One thing you do is you lower fees.
The other thing you do is you are essentially building these
as, you know, I think of it as, instead of being dependent
on Visa and their APIs and all of their other kinds of things.
Now you have a thousand companies with different APIs
and who knows what the rules are building on top of them.
I think if you go look inside of these payment processor
companies like Stripe, they have these massive teams
that are going and dealing with all of these special cases.
And then that's what makes the businesses valuable
is that they've done so much kind of grind work.
So if you imagine a world where you have sort of
this blockchain based infrastructure and the ideal case,
you have this unified global network payments become
like email in the web or it's just sort of this global protocol
and you're running, you know, I'm sending you dollars
or euros and you have these compliance
and charge back services on top kind of bundled.
Then you have this sort of, you know, universal global APIs
is what we call composability.
You can build services on top that a relatively small company
without this giant integration teams can build a service
that's like a fraud service or a charge back service.
Or, you know, like, look, a big, big problem right now
is invoice fraud.
Most businesses right there sending out a lot of them
are sending out millions of dollars a day
and they're basically getting a PDF or a piece of paper
and it says you owe me $100,000 and they've checked the address
and you'll see all these notices now, like,
make sure you call them.
So like the best practice now is to actually,
like, literally pick up the phone
and make sure you hear the person's voice and...
- Very efficient, very efficient process.
- Really that secure.
I mean, in a world where we're all carrying around these,
you know, supercomputers that have perfect facial detection
and cryptography, like it just seems kind of strange, right?
And so, you know, these companies like Stripe,
because they've kind of done what a blockchain would do
and built this integration layer with all of these services,
they can then start to build, essentially,
reputation services on top that say,
okay, this sender is valid and this one is, you know,
like a whitelist approach, the way you do with email.
But if you had this global blockchain payment system,
you could imagine a world where then all these people
are building lots of startups and big companies
are building essentially reputation services
and other kinds of things around it,
which I think would have all these secondary benefits
beyond just the fee reduction, right, it would reduce fraud,
make it more reliable, you could build reputation systems.
You could do all the things you'd done on the internet.
Like you think about email as a protocol,
we now have all these interesting services on top
because it was a global open protocol.
- And we see that in the market.
Like I spent a lot of them talking to Fintechs to say,
how are you looking to expand your payment capabilities?
And a lot of them are saying stablecoins
because now instead of them having to go to 190 countries
and run a complicated regulatory complex,
but also technically complex.
Like I guess it's great that we're paying Stripe
to handle this complexity today.
But obviously we should be in a world
where there's an entrepreneur in Guatemala
who's connecting to stablecoins
and then like they own the relationship with the banks
and they help people offer it.
Or users just get the money on their phone
and they don't have to deal with the offering
in the first place, but you don't want to be in a world
where you're beholden to a couple of large players
to make the global payment system look coherent,
even though it fundamentally isn't coherent.
And that's what we're at now.
- Let's talk about that.
We've got a global financial system.
It's not as though you can't move money.
What's wrong with what we have right now?
- I think people would really underestimate just how broken
the system is, but also specifically how many people
are in the loop on simple payment transactions
that we all take for granted.
So we did a big study on people paying
from Vietnam to Mexico.
There's a bunch of intermediaries in there
looking at pieces of paper
and they're deciding a payment can go through.
And each of those do use a correspondent bank.
They might take $20.
They can't even estimate that amount of money in advance.
Like that's how broken the system is,
that when you go to make that transaction,
you don't even really know what the person
that aside will necessarily get.
So FX fees that are getting taken,
they're correspondent bank things.
You send a thousand bucks, you might be paying a hundred.
I mean, the numbers are, they differ quite a bit.
Like if you use modern infrastructure, it could be better.
But these are what I'd call closed loop systems
where if you want to use wise,
a great company, a portfolio company of ours,
they do a great job with this.
They've really worked within that system
to improve it as much as possible.
But you're still paying maybe 20 bucks.
Your FX is pretty high.
That should really be a dollar,
a cent, you know, an inch and a half and immediately.
- I remember we funded a company that was not in the US
and we wired traditional money to them.
And it was like a week and a half,
some crazy amount of time later.
And they were like, where's the money?
So then we went and our finance department went
and tried to track it down.
And the craziest thing to me also was,
not only was it, it ended up taking like two weeks,
but when we asked where it was,
no one seemed to know none of the banks.
But they were like, don't worry,
there's a number, a Fed reference number.
So you're okay.
And I'm kind of like, well,
this shouldn't have money be somewhere.
And like, shouldn't someone know where it is?
That's a lot of money.
So actually that was the moment where we were like,
we made the finance group,
like you guys got to switch to stablecoins.
But that was the craziest part to me.
They didn't even seem to know.
And I guess they have some system
where they can always recall it or refund you or something.
So they seem very confident about it.
But you know, just intuitively,
you're like, well, shouldn't the money be somewhere?
And like, shouldn't somebody know where the money is?
- What happened there is someone was looking
at a piece of paper with the transfer amount.
And it is didn't ship it off to the next intermediary.
Like that is really the kind of thing that's going on.
- It's literally sitting on someone's desk on paper
somewhere and that's when they don't know more.
- I mean, maybe it's in the email.
Maybe it's in a review system.
- Well, and I think, and I think it goes to,
I mean, the analogy, one analogy that we like
and people have used before is text messaging
prior to WhatsApp and these so-called over-the-top networks,
right?
So the idea was, you know, back then
you really had a patchwork of networks.
You had Verizon, AT&T, now they would cut deals
to do interoperate and then they would do international deals.
And for those old enough to remember,
you'd get these text messages if you traveled internationally
that said you're now on this different plan
and the fees were much higher.
And if you were texting someone across countries,
you'd get additional fees because it was not a true network.
There was not one network.
There were many networks.
I mean, that's also like companies like Stripe.
If you don't know the payments industry,
like why are there so many payments startups?
Like every week you'll see a FinTech payments startup.
You know, like, it's kind of weird that there's this huge
industry and by the way, very successful and profitable
Visa and MasterCard are worth over a trillion dollars
in market cap and they're just one of many intermediaries.
You know, of course, the market cap is a reflection
of Wall Street's expectations of profits.
So sometimes people say, oh, these costs are necessary
for fraud in this app.
But the reality is that these are actually profitable.
Many of these are very profitable,
so which means they're making excess above the fees.
- But to comment on that, like in FinTech,
in payments is a very high regulatory burden.
And so people have used that as an excuse
to vertically integrate.
I need to manage all this complexity.
The technology, the regulatory, the user relationship.
And when you get that kind of market dynamic,
you do have the ability to take a lot of profits.
You're the only solution in there.
What I find really fascinating about Stablecoins
is it's a horizontal layer
that people can build on really readily.
So you'll actually end up with a lot stronger
competitive dynamics on top of the payment rail
where today those are mostly captured by Visa,
by MasterCard, by the other payment intermediaries.
- I mean, the naive tech view, you know,
if you just build a new payment system
about actually understanding how the existing one works.
And naive view is, oh, you could just do this
for the cost of blockchain fees or something.
There are real costs, specifically fraud.
Now, of course, with tech,
hopefully you can reduce the fraud
and we can talk about that.
But then chargebacks, you know, a lot of these systems
promise to consumers that they can recall their money
if their merchant doesn't deliver.
And then KYCML, meaning there's legal requirements
on payment companies to make sure money
doesn't go to North Korea and, you know,
other kinds of things like that.
And those things do cost money.
The question is, you know,
if you look at retail credit card payments in the US,
whatever averages 2.5% in fees,
does it cost 2.5% in fees?
We know the answer is no,
because these companies have profits,
some significant profits.
So we know that, like, the high end of that,
what it should cost, quote unquote, you know,
is half of that, let's say, or something
because of the profits, but really,
because they're also so inefficient,
because of this patchwork, there's credible reasons
of thinking it can be significantly lower.
So if right now it's 2.5%, which is 250 basis points,
like in your analysis, Ham,
you think it can get down to 30 or something,
is that right or even less?
That's about right.
I think the cost of doing these payments could be 30.
It actually could be a lot less.
So you brought up these things.
What is Visa saying is creating these costs?
They're saying fraud, they're saying sort of
table stakes, payments products, KYC, AML.
Well, like, first of all, chargebacks?
That is something that we know of in the US,
but if you're using PIX in Brazil,
or you're using WeChat in China,
you're not expecting the payment processor
to manage your charge direct for it, out-of-band systems
that do that, that you can selectively pay for.
So you don't need to bundle these services then.
It seems better, because like, why is it just so happened
that this company that's good of payments
is also gonna be mediating disputes?
Like, it's just-
Especially 'cause you want vertical specific mediation.
If I'm in a coffee shop and I buy a coffee,
there's not a fraud risk there.
If I buy something on Amazon,
I probably would be willing to work
with like a merchant relations chargeback person.
And if I buy something from a sketchy website,
'cause I want like a new Supreme Drop,
then maybe I pay for bespoke chargeback insurance there.
But these are three very different categories of product.
And right now they're all being bundled into one
two and a half to 4% fee that these and the issues are taking.
Yeah, just to add to that,
and this goes to, for those interested,
this is what my book read right on,
is about like basically the idea that in summary,
the interesting thing we do with the internet
is we build networks on top.
You know, Twitter, email, the web,
like the most powerful digital services are networks.
The network is a digital service
that gets more valuable, the more people use it.
They're important because they help solve
information distribution and coordination problems.
And the basic thesis of the book
is that there's three known ways to build networks.
There's the sort of the original way
that the internet built networks,
which I call protocol networks,
and then it's just called protocols.
That's email in the web, they're standards,
they're almost like a language.
Everyone sort of gets together and says,
"We'll speak English, we'll speak HTTP."
And then they all build software and services
that connect to that kind of lingua franca.
And what's great about that is you end up
with something that looks a lot like a public good,
like email, like no one controls email,
and there's no one who can take money,
kind of extract money.
And protocols solve a political problem
to kind of a coordination problem.
When you build a network,
you need all the kind of participants of the network
to wanna join that network.
And if they know it's a public good,
that they can safely build on top,
and one of their competitors won't sort of secretly
own it and rug them,
they're gonna be more likely to join that network.
Then there are corporate networks.
Corporate networks are Facebook, Twitter, Visa.
It's a network, but it's very simple,
actually, architecturally, just owned by a company.
They just owned it.
Now the problem with corporate networks
is you're essentially handing all this power
over to that company.
And so, of course, a Visa and Mastercard is an example.
Post started as nonprofits,
flipped to four profits later,
jacked up their fees,
and a lot of banks weren't happy with that.
So, you know.
- There's a great book on this,
A Piece of the Action by Jonah Sarah.
- Yeah, it's a good thing to really read about.
So now, the third kind of network or blockchain networks,
in my core argument in my book,
is that it's sort of the best of both worlds.
You get a lot of the advanced functionality
of corporate networks and protocol networks
couldn't deliver,
but also the kind of public good nature and low fees
and so forth of protocol networks.
The way I would think about this in the payment context,
imagine kind of a toy scenario
where you have an imaginary country with 10 banks
that want to build a payment system together.
Okay, they have those three choices.
Now, the problem is,
the protocol networks in computer science parlance
are stateless, state meaning storage in the computers,
and you don't have storage,
and there's no kind of ledger or place to keep balances,
just this architecturally, this is the way it works.
So, with email, like I sent an email to somebody,
and then they received email,
but there's no central place
where the emails are kept and the records are kept.
Now, money is just different than email in that sense,
and that you do need to keep central records, right?
If you look back 20, 25 years ago,
there were various attempts.
There's a originally HDP itself, the web, had a spec,
I think it was a 402, was the error code.
There was a payment required.
There was a placeholder put in there
that were gonna have payments.
Yeah, more people are probably familiar
with error 404 when a website URL can't be found,
but there is an error 402, like you're saying, with payments.
So, you can't do that.
And then if you go ask these guys,
the Goldman Sachs, or the Chase Banks, or Citibanks,
or whatever, hey, let's go do it,
and I'm gonna start a company,
and it'll be the intermediary,
and it'll run the network.
None of them will trust me.
They'll like, why would we do that?
Because you're just gonna do what everyone does
when they build a network.
They'll start with low fees,
and then they'll raise the fees as they gain power, right?
And you can try the non-profit thing,
but of course, we've seen many cases
where non-profits flip to for-profits.
That doesn't really mean much.
The other challenge is,
if you defang the intermediary,
corporate intermediary too much,
then how do they go hire people?
How do they, like, they need to themselves become valuable
to recruit people, and build a company,
and build great technology?
Right, if they don't extract,
their lunch is gonna get eaten
by another corporation that does extract.
Yeah, that's right.
The competitive dynamics of tech
are such that it's very hard,
like, just as is how it works.
So, blockchains are really powerful
in that they kind of are the best of both worlds.
You can build stateful protocols,
you can keep a ledger,
you can do all these powerful things
you wanna do with payments,
but you can do it in a way
that there is no central, powerful intermediary.
Architecturally, that's the core innovation of a blockchain,
is that you have these so-called consensus mechanism,
game theoretic mechanism pioneered by Bitcoin
and expanded on by later blockchains.
And I think about what Bitcoin is.
Bitcoin, what it essentially is, right,
is it's a centralized ledger.
It keeps track of who has how many Bitcoins,
but it does it in a way that there's no Bitcoin company.
There's no one behind it, right?
It's a group of people coming together
using this kind of game theoretic mechanism
that provides the core service
of a financial network, a payment network,
without any intermediary.
Now it has pros and cons and its architecture and fees,
and you can have a whole debate about it.
There's been a lot of work since then,
and specifically in what we will call
the programmable blockchain world of like Ethereum and Solana,
to kind of expand on that, reduce the fees,
improve the functionality, performance reliability,
and so forth.
And that's gotten us to a point now,
which as of a year and a half ago,
Sam was saying we've now had an important milestone
of you can now send stablecoins under one second
and under one penny.
And by the way, this is not the theoretical download
coin-based wallet, and then try it.
I just tried it yesterday to double confirm it.
- I've got a fun, a fun story for you about this.
I was playing basketball the other day.
I rent out this gym,
and so I collect payment from everyone at the end of the day.
And this guy comes up to me and he's like,
hey, you're saying, I see you on Twitter.
You love stablecoins.
So he says, what do I pay you in USDC?
So yeah, it's 20 bucks.
Here's my ETH address, so I'm SamBroner. ETH.
He sends me 20 bucks, costs like a small fraction of a cent.
And I then put that into a lending protocol.
So I'm like earning yield on it.
And about 24 hours later,
I've made enough in interest that I paid back the fee.
Now, like what a crazy dynamic that is.
Like, I mean, now I've made more than 20 bucks.
If that was in Venmo, I wanted the money right away.
It would have taken me three days to get it out of Venmo,
let alone like the nonsense interest rate
I'm getting in my bank.
So I get the money in a second.
It's mine. I can send it to someone else.
Or I can sweep as in and just like,
put that money into saying that's earning interest.
And suddenly I'm out on top of games on Saturday
by like Monday afternoon.
I've made my money back.
And you just can't do that on normal rails at all.
- That's really interesting
when you consider a lot of FinTech business models.
I mean, you mentioned Venmo.
They're just banking on a lot of people
leaving money in their accounts.
And then they get to collect interest on them.
- Yeah.
- But you're able to actually earn interest
on the stablecoins that you were sent.
- Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
So look, these institutions, they money in a couple of ways.
That interest, we call it Nim, this net interest margin.
There's other ways to get paid.
Like they'll also charge you when you try to take the money out.
And so like, if you try to withdraw money from Venmo
immediately rather than waiting the normal three or four days,
they'll also charge you 3% there.
And so no matter how you slice it,
you're getting a pretty raw deal.
What is so interesting is that because only certain institutions
have permission from the government,
they have regulatory lock-in to hold your money,
there's not a very competitive market here.
We should all be getting 4% interest on our savings.
That's a little bit better than inflation.
And we should benefit from the sort of growth of the economy.
That's how the world should work.
Instead, Bank of America or Venmo or PayPal
is sitting on your money and giving you nothing
while they take that home for,
"Look, they've got a nice product,
but I think we could recreate in a weekend
what we couldn't recreate is the network effects that they have.
And so they get to be extracted with those network effects.
And that's what they've done to date.
But there is a better way like this basketball scenario
where I get the money on day one,
and then I get interest as well.
- It reminds me of AOL, for the longest time,
was just collecting fees from zombie accounts.
People who hadn't actually severed their relationship.
They're just paying subscriptions every year,
thinking like that's how they get internet access,
just making lots of money off this,
well beyond the point when you need to actually pay
for that subscription to get internet access.
So how long is that interest generating business model
going to be sustaining these FinTechs?
- So look, we're seeing the first use cases
of stablecoin payments happen in the wild right now.
And it's different by geography and by user.
In the US for wealthy users,
they're thinking my credit card rocks.
I get 3% off everything.
It's accepted everywhere.
I don't really need to change.
But the PSPs, so Stripe,
whoever runs sort of the payment terminal at a coffee shop,
these guys are getting like 10 basis points
and they're actually giving most of the money
to the issuing banks and Visa.
And so those payment service providers,
they have an incentive to switch over to crypto rails
'cause they can offer users a better product
while taking maybe 10 X more fees.
Like they could charge 0.5% instead of 0.1%
while still offering the merchant a better deal.
So that dynamic will encourage payment service providers
in the US to switch.
- They can raise their fees, get more money
and yet still drop the cost for customers.
- 'Cause they're cutting out the intermediary
and it's an unbelievable opportunity.
We've seen Stripe start to go in this direction.
So they're the first to turn it on
so they get this first mover advantage.
They're charging 1.5% for stablecoin payments.
That's pretty high.
I think they're probably making 1% on every transaction
but it's still a great deal for merchants
because merchants are used to paying 3%.
The merchants love it and Stripe loves it
'cause they take home a lot more money at the end of the day.
So in the US, I think that's where we'll first see it
where users aren't gonna realize
that they're using crypto necessarily
but the payment service providers
are gonna be really pushing this new angle.
In lower income or high inflation countries,
people actually wanna hold stablecoins directly.
They'll interact with it.
They'll pay with it.
We do have a ways to go though
until everyone feels really comfortable with stablecoins.
We need to create what some people call a stablecoin mullet.
It's stablecoins in the back
but it looks like you're used to in the front
and people just get cheaper products that work better
but they integrate where users already are.
Another example just to linger on this for a second is Skype.
People think of it as sort of video conferencing
but when it first got started,
one of the key features they enabled
is that from your computer,
you could call someone's landline.
And so that interoperability
is part of what created the onboarding.
Stablecoins probably need to have that moment
where from my wallet that holds stablecoins,
I can hit anyone else's account
no matter what denomination or technology it is.
That backwards could be huge.
And then eventually we're gonna end up with WhatsApp
and FaceTime and things like once people fully get oriented
to this new world,
but we need to have Skype-like technology
to integrate and be backwards compatible.
- How do you achieve that backwards compatibility?
I mean, if we're talking about how stablecoins
and blockchains disintermediate,
how are you gonna get existing players on board with that?
- One of the things that we think about the most
on the investing side is who is really gonna help us,
help the world move forward with this new technology?
The banks probably aren't gonna do it.
They love the current situation.
They're very stagnant.
The FinTechs are extremely excited.
They think, wow, I can go to market in 190 countries.
I can be universally on everywhere.
I can work with service providers,
basically entrepreneurs who are building functionality.
I don't wanna deal with.
I wanna focus on my core product
and let them move the rest forward.
There are things also that we need to build
on top of stablecoins to reach table stakes payments capability.
So Chris mentioned chargebacks earlier,
but like we also need escrow subscriptions, refunds.
We need vaulting, which is where you store
a payment credential on a website.
Like when you go to Amazon, the credit card's already there.
We need promotions.
We need people to be able to easily discount.
We need integration into ERPs,
enterprise resource planning tools
so that the CFO can look at the state of their business
and say, I've got this many stablecoins.
I'm gonna pay my supplier tomorrow.
They're gonna get it in exchange for this invoice.
Those are the integrations that need to be built
if we wanna reach mass market.
And there's a huge opportunities
in each of those capabilities
for people to reach traditional payment rail parity.
There's another issue that I love talking about
'cause I was briefly working at the Boston Federal Reserve Bank,
but the singleness of money,
which is that I trust that a dollar in my wallet
is the same as a dollar in your bank account
and is worth a dollar in Chris's Venmo.
That singleness of money took a long time to develop.
I wrote a piece on the history of banking
and how that relates to stablecoins.
And before 1910, you really weren't positive
that a dollar bill in your hand was worth a dollar bill
in your hand 'cause you had to trust the credit worthiness
of the bank that it was associated with.
These were bank-issued dollars.
And today, through a huge amount of regulation,
but also sophisticated risk management, interoperability,
clearinghouses, we've created a world
where we do get dollar parity,
where we have this trust that dollars are always worth the same.
Today, we don't have that in stablecoins.
- But that's a big part of why regulation's so important.
- Let's jump in with the regulation question.
- Currently, there is no kind of clear regulation
around stablecoins and just more broadly in crypto.
There's laws passed in the 1930s and later
that can arguably be interpreted to apply here,
but there's a lot of confusion.
- When you say things that could apply
from the 1930s, are we talking about like--
- Yeah, securities law, how we test.
And this is like 1930s kind of stuff.
And like certain tokens or commodities,
the regulators in the US have said
that Bitcoin and Ethereum are commodities
and other tokens might be securities
and where do you draw the line?
And what we want, what entrepreneurs want
are very clear, bright line rules
so they know they can stay within them
that allow for innovation, but put guardrails around
and prevent another FTX from happening.
I mean, I think these catastrophic failures,
Terra Luna FTX, first and foremost,
we're devastating to the customers
who lost money and things.
But also we're devastating to the industry, right?
I mean, destruction of trust
and just sort of general harm to the broader
blockchain technology movement was huge.
And that looms over us.
When you take stablecoins, I think there's a chance
that that could happen again right now.
And it's just simply the volumes.
I mean, the stablecoins are 2X last month
or roughly or something, Visa's volume.
I mean, these are trillions of dollars in volumes.
- The first quarter of this year,
stablecoins had the most transaction volume
that they've ever had.
- So I know I'm not saying anything negative
about a specific project or anything like that,
but you just say like, if we had another catastrophe,
where would it be?
It's the things where the really high volumes are, right?
So the point is just like, first and foremost,
let's make sure there isn't a catastrophe.
And so what would you do?
This is what the pending proposed bills in Congress do,
is they have requirements.
So for example, the requirements essentially
that you're fully asset backed by high quality,
short-term financial products of treasury bills,
things like this.
If the user thinks they have a dollar,
that means they're literally in a audited US bank.
There's something that's a lot like a dollar,
like either of dollars or treasury bills.
And so the bill spells out what those assets are,
what the reserve requirements are,
spells out auditing requirements.
So you don't just take my word for it that the bank, right?
They have an actual auditor.
And all of these things would have prevented things like FTX.
I mean, it also has rules around interoperating
across countries.
It's essentially like reciprocity ideas
so that if other countries want to interoperate
with these systems, they have to have similar rules.
So, you know, this would set the template,
which would hopefully propagate out.
It's kind of a no-brainer.
I mean, look, we think a much bigger policy issue
is the broader confusion.
And so that's why that would hopefully be addressed
by what people are calling a market structure bill,
which is similar to a bill
that passed to House Representatives last year called 521.
That's really the high-level policy fix here.
Stable coins are a lower priority for us,
but it's just such a kind of no-brainer obvious thing to do
that we think should be done.
Like, why wouldn't you have regulation on these things
and have all this ambiguity?
And so that's kind of the late land.
I mean, we're hoping that there's some momentum now
to get these sort of two potential bills passed this year,
which would, I think, really clarify both stable coins
and the rest of the space.
That would also have this sort of trickle-down effect,
which is to regulate the stable coin itself,
which is kind of the app layer of these things.
But it also would put requirements
around, like, if a bank is going to issue a stable coin,
they need to make sure the underlying infrastructure
meets certain requirements as well.
So that's sort of the blockchain layer,
like Ethereum and Solana and those things.
So it's going to have this kind of trust-propagating fact
where you're going to have all of the infrastructure
will kind of have to level up and be more mature,
because that's another risk right now.
I think one other thing to think about with regulation
is it not only has the literal laws and policies
passed, but it's also an important signaling effect,
which is a lot of these institutions in the financial space
are very risk-averse.
They're very heavily regulated.
They're honestly very scared of doing anything
that gets even remotely close to something
they perceive as risky.
And to have, specifically, legislation.
So, I mean, legislation is the highest form of regulation.
It's the most powerful.
It's Congress, the United States of America,
passing a law, which is kind of from a signaling and longevity
and just all the other kinds of atmospheric surrounded
by far the strongest statement that a government can make
beyond, sort of, let's say, an agency
putting out guidance as an example.
And so that will be very important, too.
I think it will really legitimate this technology
and allow a lot of institutions who right now are on the fence.
And I've heard this, and I think Sam,
you probably have, too, directly from these institutions.
They're waiting for that kind of stamp of approval
that legislation would provide.
- It's probably where it's quickly summarizing
the state of regulation on stablecoins.
And we have these two acts, Genius and Stable Act,
that are currently being talked about in Congress and seem.
You know, really exciting.
It's, like, clear rules for the road.
It's robust consumer protections.
And it's AML, KYC, that makes sense for payments.
And then the OCC has greenlit bank crypto activities.
So now bank's concussity.
Crypto assets hold, typical reserves.
And then the SEC has clarified that
stablecoins are not securities if they're used for payments,
if they're appropriately backed.
Things that work with the proposed demo coin bills,
the Genius and Stable Acts.
- The Fed also recently withdrew its bank guidance
where it required banks to seek permission
if they were gonna do anything crypto related.
So now that's cleared a way for them to get into this.
- Yeah, but you don't think you build, like, I don't know.
I mean, I've spent my career on the internet
and I've just very influenced by how the internet policy worked.
But what was so important for the internet
was legislation passed in the '90s.
And specifically, the '96 Telecom Act
was a landmark bill that had a whole bunch of things,
including Section 230,
which is really the foundation
of how you could build on the internet,
because you knew that, I mean, it can be changed,
but it's in practice, effectively permanent,
because it's very hard to change.
And Section 230 as an example,
enabled marketplaces and social networks to exist,
because it said that without that,
all these things would have gotten sued into oblivion,
and it gave them some reasonable kind of safe harbor
that tried to balance protections for users and platforms.
And that's very important,
because if you're an entrepreneur and back in the 2000s,
for example, who was thinking of devoting your life
to building this,
you wanted to know that it wouldn't be something
that would just get turned off
with a new political environment, right?
You need to solve a foundation to build on.
And so that was passed, and that was the foundation.
I mean, the internet wouldn't have existed.
The US wouldn't be the leader in the internet, in my view.
And so we just want to have a similar thing here.
And at Sam's point, there's different details on the bills.
Like one controversial aspect in the stablecoin bill
is whether the stablecoins can provide yield
directly to consumers as someone who believes tech
should mostly benefit consumers.
I think that would be good.
If consumers could get there 4% and not 0%.
- For what it's worth,
that's not an issue that I particularly care about.
- Look, I mean, there's a political realities,
which is that stablecoins as payments,
which would mean sort of no giving yield,
is something we can get political alignment around.
If you start to give yield,
you start to really compete with the banks,
and then it becomes a much more fraught political discussion
because it's a huge industry, incumbent industry.
We're going to oppose things.
So yes, and also I think the other thing I would say
is from an incentive point of view,
if you want these to be used as payments,
if you're getting 4%,
you're not going to want to give it up as much, right?
Like, so if there's 0%,
you're going to have much higher velocity.
And so they are going to be like,
let this bill pass as it is, build this payment system,
and you can build other systems for building yield.
- That's how I would like it to play out.
I mean, I want the distributors,
people who are giving people stablecoins
to be able to have a small cut at the apple
to get a benefit for distributing stablecoins.
And so we're going to build a more competitive environment
where people are going to get more of their yield.
And look, there's a difference between spending money
and saving money.
I'm happy if when you're saving,
you put it into a DeFi protocol where you get 5%,
or you leave it with Coinbase where you get 5%.
But when you're spending it, you get zero,
and then you use the programability of stablecoins
to sweep it back into that yield-bearing holding spot.
The key thing is we need to get legislation done
so that people can actually use these things for payments
and make for a better product overall.
- Again, going back, these are networks,
and networks have network effects,
meaning they get more valuable
to more nodes on the network.
And we're in a situation here with stablecoins
where 99% of the nodes that matter are highly regulated.
I mean, it's kind of remarkable
that we have trillions of dollars in monthly volume
where 99% of the participants of the network
feel like they can't join the network right now.
So the big unlock is one actual rules
that protect you from an FTX.
And then number two is now you've suddenly unlocked
this 99% of the world to join this network.
- Are you expecting those volumes to explode then
after regulation gets passed?
- I think it'll be like anything, right?
Like the stripes of the world, the super smart FinTechs
have already done it, they're already at volume scale,
and they'll just ramp that, right?
Here, the benefit is just so obvious
that I think it's gonna be clearly dominant.
Specific timing is harder to predict.
- Look, the ones that are really innovative
are already doing this, and they're reaching out to us
and saying, yo, who do we work with to make this happen?
And then some of the banks are reticent
'cause they don't want to give up the current model
where they get a lot of the benefit of how payments work.
And so over the next six months, 12 months, two years,
I expect to see a lot of people helping FinTechs,
helping these banks move forward and adopts Democrats
'cause they're just so obvious
that it's a better solution for them,
even if they don't want to do it today.
- Yeah, at some point, the bit flips
where like if you're most of the world
they're conservative middle managers or whatever.
At some point, the bit flips where it's now
greater risk to your career to not do it than to do it,
right, and it works hard from that point,
but at some point, that will flip.
- Network effects do have a lot of gravity.
Like if 30% of people or a lot of people in one geography
have access to stablecoins,
you don't actually need on and off ramp infrastructure anymore,
but you need it in order to get there.
And so there's gonna be a point where
stablecoins become default on, everyone has to have it.
That's when the network effect is really strong,
and that's where we're gonna see
that the laggards are gonna get killed
until they update their infrastructure
to allow stablecoins to be integrated natively.
- So the value to consumers seems pretty clear,
cheaper, faster, global, instant payments,
but from a business perspective,
if you are dealing with stablecoins,
if you're issuing them, distributing them,
is this a good business to be in?
As more competition enters, as interest rates decline,
as different players start offering yield,
if that's allowed, I mean PayPal is now offering
close to 4% yields on stablecoin holdings
in their Venmo and PayPal wallets.
As you start having this competition
and these different kind of macroeconomic changes happen,
does the stablecoin business remain a good business to be in?
- So right now, if you are not a financial institution,
you are not in the payments business anyway.
You have to pay these guys
in order to use payment rails every time you do it.
So if you're a business who's thinking,
"I've got a cool feature.
"I think if we did 10 cents for a like or tipping creators,
"you've got to go find a service provider
"that you're paying a lot of money to
"in order to implement that feature."
In the world with stablecoins,
you can just build it just as easily
as you can set up a database.
So is it worthwhile to get into stablecoins?
Well, maybe for the banks,
this is not the best thing in the world.
But if you are an innovative business
that wants to include money,
one of the most basic things that we use all day
in your product without going and dealing
with some extractive entity,
you're so excited about the opportunity
you now have with stablecoins.
Now, for the FinTechs,
they're also beholden to the banks in some ways.
So they're gonna be the first to adopt.
It makes their infrastructure a lot easier to manage
and build.
And then there's gonna be some innovative banks
who say, "Look, we've got this amount of deposits today.
"We're getting that interest margin on it,
"but we're not gonna go away.
"We're in the tail end of our ability
"to have deposits be locked up in this account.
"And so we're gonna have to start working
"with modern rails, offer new tooling.
"And banks are always resistant to new tooling.
"But they're gonna have to get on board
"when they realize that that's how payments work going forward.
"And for the really innovative ones,
"they're actually gonna be able to expand
"their net interest margin to dollars
"that are off their platform.
"And so an innovative bank would say,
"Actually, we could expand our deposits
"by embracing stablecoins.
"But so far, the banks haven't been that forward looking.
"I'm excited to see the first banks who do do that
"because they're gonna get a lot of market share that way
"and expand revenue.
"We just haven't seen it from the banks yet."
- Yeah, I mean, it's a good question.
I mean, like in our job, what we do right is we say,
"Okay, what are the big trends coming
"and how do we bet on them?"
And so the stablecoins are probably
the biggest, most obvious trend happening in this area.
And we've had this conversation
like how do we make a bet on them?
And to be candid, it's much harder than in most tech trends.
And that is because of the things we were saying earlier
in the podcast, which is, it's kind of a public good.
I mean, it's just like building kind of a highway system
for the people to send stuff cheaply
you're removing the intermediary.
So you can't invest in the intermediary as an example
because that's the whole point as you're removing them.
There's a typical effect of these kinds of information
and internet businesses is you grow the market,
you grow GDP, you grow usage.
So they'll be, if this works, you lower fees
and there'll be more payments and more economic activity.
But the take rates will go down, right?
The amount of sort of extract will go down.
Now, that said, with all these new opportunities,
there's always like often there are, you know,
new software businesses and example,
like if every bank suddenly wants stable an infrastructure,
they would presumably want to buy that software
and not build it.
So if somebody will provide that software
and that's sort of a classic enterprise software business,
but that's like, you know, that's a software model
where you sell them licensed software
or subscription software or whatever it is.
But to me, honestly, the most obvious investment opportunity
is in the underlying infrastructure, right?
These stablecoins run on blockchains.
And specifically the dominant, I think by far,
right now is Ethereum is the dominant one for stablecoins
and then you have others like so on.
- Tron also with tether is.
- And then I think, unfortunately,
with some of the other ones like that, like Tron,
like I don't think that's a, you know,
that has the right security characteristics.
- And it's expensive.
- Yeah, it's very, it's like, has shocked at the fees
I saw recently, like $6.00.
- Yeah, $4.00 to $6.00, yeah.
- It's not really decentralized.
So it's not, I mean, you haven't really removed
the intermediary.
So, you know, if you take the subset of blockchains
where stablecoins are popular
and I think have the proper kind of security
and trust characteristics,
you end up with things like, you know,
Ethereum, Solana, L2s,
you also need kind of layers on top of that.
So you need bridges,
you need other kinds of infrastructure.
Yeah, and that's sort of a bank shot
as an investment that's sort of indirect.
But I think that, I don't know,
at least from my thinking about it,
that's kind of what I come back to is like,
okay, this is going to popularize all of this infrastructure.
And, you know, maybe there'll be some adjacent software stuff,
but it is probably the least investable crypto thing
that's happened since the beginning, I would say almost.
It is much harder to directly invest in.
- It's like such a paradox.
Like it is the thing that's popping off the journey.
- That's the irony.
And using crypto, it's easier to invest than to get usage.
And here's the opposite.
It's like, this is something that's like clear product
market fit and usage and it's harder to invest in.
- There really are opportunities.
I mean, I spent a lot of time talking to businesses
that are building on top of stablecoins.
- I think Jam is more,
I'm a little more bullish on this than I am.
I feel like it's more of a public good,
but yeah, go ahead, sir.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I mean, look, I think we have to have valuations
be it appropriately priced.
Like these are FinTech businesses.
These are not crypto businesses with network effects.
But if you're offering table stakes payments,
subscriptions, refunds, chargebacks,
vaulting, promotions, we invested in a loop who does that.
Like, you know, that's a real business
that people really need if they want to use stablecoins
in the real world.
And then you've got the enterprise integrations.
We've got on and off ramping.
I think that there's huge improvements they'd be made
in with, on top of account abstraction
to make it easier for people to have a wallet
where they custody their own assets.
Of course, like we're going to need a little bit better
privacy, but compliant privacy in payments.
And that's more at the infrastructure level,
but people are going to feel that at the app layer.
And for enterprises, like there's features
like treasury management and collateral ability.
These are all large FinTech oriented opportunities
that I'm extremely eager to see entrepreneurs build.
And they're going to have to have deep understanding
of stablecoins.
And I guess to tie back into our focus,
which is on blockchain networks,
there's a lot of ways to use blockchain incentives
to build those networks so they're stronger,
identifiable earlier, you know, break the log jam
of extractive networks.
And so I'm excited to visit that do that in particular
who build these sort of more FinTech oriented ideas,
but with blockchain ideals.
And we're starting to see it.
We're starting to meet them now.
- Yeah, I guess I would just say I look at the,
well, my historically and just one of my area of focus
has always been network effect businesses.
That's what I've always done, not enterprise software.
So there probably are in fairness,
like kind of like temper my statement earlier,
probably a lot of sort of enterprise software business,
et cetera, which is not what I've personally
historically done or been good at.
But that goes to the just one last thing is that
that's the whole point of stablecoins.
Is it you're removing the ability for investors
and entrepreneurs to extract,
which I think is a good thing for the world.
And I think it's a good thing for blockchains
and generally to have this as a use case.
But to me, it undermines kind of what I typically
have tried to invest in mature kind of networks.
- Yeah, the big network that has not been solved yet
is liquidity.
And liquidity has a surprisingly strong network effect.
Today, if you tried to switch.
- It's an equity, I mean, like interoperability
between like switching from one blockchain.
- Switching from one currency to another.
So if I wanna take 10 million USDC
and turn it into 10 million in Pi USD, two stablecoins,
both I think highly compliant, well-backed.
I'm gonna get some slippage there.
And by slippage, I mean, instead of 10 million on the other side,
I'm gonna get 9,900,000 even on the deepest liquidity pools.
And that's a network effect in that
as more people use these currencies,
we'll have deeper liquidity and much tighter spreads.
Whoever cracks that, whoever figures out,
I make sure that we can redeem one stablecoin
for another stablecoin at par
is gonna have a huge and exciting network effect.
- Interesting.
So your point being that if you wanna use this money,
if you wanna use it across various networks,
various apps, whatever, if you're transacting,
you might actually lose a little bit of the value there
that might go to the system.
And in order for this to really take off,
consumers are gonna want to know that one USDC,
one Pi USD always equals one dollar.
Users know that today, but at the largest scales
and in the most esoteric scenarios,
it breaks down a little bit.
And we need to build systems that make sure
that it's always true.
We get this true singleness of money.
And there's a lot of ways to solve it.
One is through clearinghouses,
another is through shared collateral,
a third might be through regulations combined
with really well-tuned AMMs or intent protocols.
I think we've got a lot of people working on the problem,
but it's one of the large outstanding problems
that probably needs to be solved first.
- I wanna zoom out for a second,
because I think some of our listeners might ask themselves,
why is a blockchain necessary at all
to do some of these things?
I mean, you could look at some services that are coming up,
like you've got the PIX real-time payment system in Brazil
that manages to do really, really instant cheap fast payments.
So what is the advantage of using a blockchain?
Why is that superior or necessary compared to
perhaps more traditional approaches
or just alternate approaches
that could conceivably be applied?
- So PIX is amazing.
Like we should all congratulate the Brazilian government
on implementing a great new payment rail.
But there's two problems with it.
One is really clear,
and one is a little bit harder to think through.
So the first is that you can't pay
someone internationally via PIX.
So it really is a closed loop system
where it's not so hard to build on top PIX,
but it's hard to have PIX interoperability
with other countries.
And so if you wanna do international payments,
which happen all the time in enormous volumes,
then you can't use that system.
And the second thing is,
I don't really want to have the government
running my payment rails that directly.
It has a couple of negative externalities.
One is this less competition.
What happens when something better than PIX comes out?
Is the government really gonna replace it?
Probably not.
But on blockchain rails,
you could incrementally improve the quality of the product.
The second is around monetary expansion.
We wanna make sure that we can have institutions like banks,
lending, keeping the economy active,
making dynamic choices to help people in communities
invest, save, earn, spend,
without it being tied to a central bank, digital currency.
That would be very constrictive,
and it would erode privacy, erode trust,
and wouldn't lead to the competitive environment
that we wanna see where entrepreneurs can build
new monetary systems that allow people to take risks
and do so safely and spend money freely.
So PIX is impressive,
but I don't think it's the way
we wanna have international payments work,
and it's probably also not the way that in the U.S.
we wanna have local payments work
because it leads to this sort of constrained supply of cash.
- And like this is going back to the book,
I was talking about the different kinds of networks.
I mean, one way to think about blockchains
is they solve not just a technical problem,
but a political problem.
Political in a sense of getting a bunch of parties
who don't fully trust each other to agree on something.
And so in that case, let's just say PIX,
they go and maybe they convince some friendly governments,
but are they really gonna convince
whatever it is, 190 key governments to agree to something?
The answer is none of them are gonna agree to something
unless I think it's truly neutral.
Blockchains are the first thing that have come along
since the advent of the internet
that have the functionality sufficient
to do these kinds of use cases like payments,
but also are truly credibly neutral.
And they're credibly neutral
because they don't have an owner,
they're open source code running on these decentralized blockchains.
And so they have the same kind of trust properties
as open source software.
I mean, that's why things like Linux have been so successful, right?
Is it you can dislike the makers of Linux
and dislike the country they live in?
It doesn't matter because you just have the code, right?
You can trust the code and blockchains have that same property.
- That's a really good articulation.
So you're in the design space,
you're trading off how centralized or decentralized
you're gonna have.
And when you go with a centralized approach like PIX,
you get platform risk, trust dependencies,
and maybe a lack of interoperability on a kind of global scale.
Whereas when you go in a decentralized direction,
you get this sort of credibly neutral platform
that everybody can join,
comfortable knowing they can't get rubbed or biased against.
I've got a question about the branding for stablecoins.
It is sort of like incredibly good marketing.
On the one hand, I mean,
there's a question of like, we call them stablecoins.
Are they stable? I think regulation will go
toward helping solve that.
But then there's also the coin question.
We had some of our other teammates on a recent podcast
where we talked about the differences
in types of tokens that are out there.
And there's a lot of confusion around people thinking about
them as cryptocurrencies or coins.
And I wonder if calling them stablecoins
is that lens through which we look at stablecoins
as coins, as payment, as currency,
does that limit our imagination
about what we can do with these types of instruments?
- Yeah, I don't know.
I mean, I think like a lot of things in tech
and specifically crypto, these naming notes,
there wasn't like a committee that sat around
and did a study of this, some hacker somewhere,
and then it became popular.
And it's probably not the greatest name, to be honest,
for both stable and coin, right?
I mean, maybe at some point people just call them
ideally just dollars, you know?
Like you just go to your account and you see dollars
and it's a new rail.
There will probably be, I think in the legislation,
some kind of actual control of the words.
You know, you can't put the word dollar
if you're not doing certain things, which is important.
So I think it's a good point, I don't know.
Like in tech, the products end up being the marketing.
Not the words as much.
So like the words sort of matter,
but then at some point they don't like,
there's been so many bad brand names in history of tech.
People debated Google and Twitter and all these things.
Yahoo!
But what happened is the product was so overwhelmingly good.
I think I'll say in the case of Google
that it almost just changed what the words mean, right?
- It also might remain a investing term
because when we see stable coins go mainstream,
I don't think people are gonna be thinking
about this category name.
They're just gonna say,
"Oh, I've got some money in my wallet
and I can send it to you immediately."
I mean, what do you call your Venmo bounce?
Like you don't really say Venmo bucks.
So I'll keep calling it stable coins
when I'm looking for companies,
but I'm not sure our end users are gonna,
you know, use that term in the long term.
- So from a consumer perspective,
you're expecting that this is going to be abstracted away.
- Yeah.
- Okay, so based on where we are now
with the adoption of stable coins,
really there's incredible growth going on.
I mean, last year the circulating supply of stable coins
was like 130 billion.
Now it's like not quite double that, but almost.
Yeah, okay, so maybe it is double.
So there's incredible growth.
What changes about crypto, about the crypto industry,
what becomes possible with this new piece of infrastructure,
this new technology?
And what changes about the world around us
and the tech and the products that we use?
- Yeah, this is my sort of favorite thing to talk about.
It's like, if stable coins win, everybody succeeds.
What happens next?
Well, I'm making payments in stable coins.
What if I wanted to get alone on my stable coin holdings?
But I want to track where a package is on blockchain rails.
But I wanna use a social network that has my identity
that is tied to my payments.
There's a lot of services that once I'm paying every day,
want to move on chain due to that gravity.
Identity is the most obvious.
Then social networks begin to form on top of that.
Then so do you customer to merchant relationships and so forth.
And so stable coins are just sort of the first step,
but all of the other on chain products that we know of
seem much more likely to succeed
when people are already using dollars on chain.
- This is partly 'cause it's such a big, like right now,
the UX of getting money onto a blockchain is just,
there's a hurdle.
And so if you can provide this initial use case
and get people on there, they have a wallet,
they've got the software, they've got some money there
that you've gotten over a major hurdle
that was inhibiting growth.
- And so as you begin to move payments on chain,
a lot of additional things begin to quickly follow.
And those opportunities are potentially even like bigger
and more creative than just the simple payments,
just the simple exchange.
Now we go category by category and say,
for this industry, if you were to move payments on chain,
what are the other things you'd wanna have
be tied into payments?
Identity is the most obvious.
Fraud protection is another one.
Lending is a third, but we see in basically every category,
there are services you might wanna add to payments
that should also be on chain,
living with that atomic payment product.
And once people start using payments,
the rest of the on-chain ecosystem is gonna continue to grow.
- If you had to make an informed guess,
how long would you expect this to play out?
- I think that in two years,
we're gonna see stablecoins turned on as an option
in many, many, many places.
Already, merchants are offering online,
stablecoins very readily.
I think international, it's gonna be even more popular
because internationally, credit cards,
users are less beholden to credit cards.
And so it'll be easier to add a new rail.
But there's many ways that adoption's gonna happen.
So one is this consumer scenario
that we're walking through right now.
The consumer scenario is a little harder in the US.
It has to be driven by payment service providers.
But in countries with inflationary currencies
or with lower card penetration
or more challenging payment technology,
stablecoins might be a first-class citizen from day one
or people are like, oh, I can pay for my phone.
This is unbelievable and this option didn't exist.
I wanna hold money in dollar-denominated
stablecoins in particular.
Anyway, there's a huge, huge structural demand
for dollars in much of the global south.
And then internationally, for businesses that work internationally,
they're gonna be saying,
I did not like dealing with the banks
when I was doing international money movement.
It takes a long time.
I have to have a whole team dedicated
to managing the process.
It's a major headache.
And I'm gonna switch small businesses.
This is medium business, large enterprises
with sophisticated treasury management.
All of them are gonna move to stablecoins
'cause they're strictly better technology.
So these three groups, PSPs in the US,
regular consumers in the global south,
and then enterprise driven demand
in the international business community.
Those are probably the three different drivers of adoption.
When will you see it?
When you go online to buy something
or when you go into a restaurant?
Well, if you use Blackbird, you can see it right now.
And if you use Stripe, you can see it right now online.
But when you're gonna see it everywhere
and if you're really gonna notice it,
it's gonna probably require some go-to-market energy
using the savings in order to incentivize users
to switch to the new payment rail.
And then it's gonna require the growing network effects
and growing acceptance of stablecoins
as just another dollar two to five years.
Is the simple answer to your question,
but that's the longer story.
Let's zero in on that just for one second.
We talk about stablecoins as being global by default,
but the world is a big place.
What regions or markets do you expect to get uptake first?
How is this gonna play out on global scale?
I mean, we cannot overstate the structural demand for dollars.
A huge number of people,
they have a currency that's very inflationary
and their version of savings is having money in dollars.
It's not putting money in this hot market.
It's having physical cash, US dollars.
I talked last, last quarters,
last like three months or so
to about 30 companies that were doing remittances
on stablecoin rails.
And many of them were growing at 10% a month
on top of $1 million to $10 million total payment volume a month.
So we're talking just like sort of an industry
that's growing it at 10% a month, unbelievable growth.
And that's because if you're in Argentina,
you used to have to go to a,
I mean, I did this.
I was in Argentina two years ago.
I had brought specifically,
'cause a friend who recommended it,
crisp new $100 bills.
They prefer the crisp new ones.
I get in my hotel.
They call a guy who looks like a drug dealer to come in.
He's got a bag full of Argentinian pesos.
I gave him my $100.
He double checks with the new ones.
He gives me the preferred exchange rate
because the new dollars are so valuable.
This is not an exchange rate I could get in a bank, by the way.
This is like a illegal exchange rate.
And to show practices, guys,
he's just churning, counting money to give me pesos.
That gives you a sense for how badly people want dollars there.
They prefer the crisp new US dollars because,
I mean, who doesn't?
It's nice.
You know, no bends and wrinkles and folds.
No, but it's because people are like treating this
as their savings.
So they want it to be really premium.
They want to know it's like the most accepted version
of the dollar.
But this is just so fun.
It's like you bought your friendly card to be,
you have the clean metal like, you want to make a sound
when you drop it on the table when you want to have to flex
your biceps to hold your credit card.
But there's just like an absolutely better solution now,
which is you could just hold stablecoins.
Maybe you don't need paper at all.
You might not need paper at all.
I think that, you know,
one thing that's interesting to think through
is what the state of issuers is going to be.
So right now, 90% of stablecoins are dollar-denominated,
fiat reserve, so backed by treasuries.
I think the market share is like,
Tether has 60% and Circle has maybe 40%.
Is that right?
Or maybe I'm overestimating--
Of the 90%, that's right.
The other 10% of stablecoins are either
what I would call asset backed,
but there's CDPs collateralized debt deposit stablecoins.
It's like Maker is the most famous.
And I kind of like these CDPs, actually.
They've proven to be very resilient, very safe,
but they're not super capital efficient.
They actually kind of mimic what banks do today
where they take in assets like mortgages and loans
and they turn that into monetary expansion.
So I think that we're actually going to see more CDPs.
There's other things like these strategy backed
synthetic dollars that I think of more like a dollar hedge fund
that I actually don't count those as stablecoins
because those seem to me to be an investment product
where you should really diligence
the underlying strategy being used.
Anyway, so we look at these sort of three categories.
Fiat Reserve is so large.
I wonder if we're going to see more competition in that space.
Already we're starting to see Fiat Reserve stablecoins
with a more default on way of distributing yield
to people who help distribute it.
So let's say I make a new payments app,
peer to peer payments app like FEMMO that uses stablecoins.
Maybe I could get a piece of the net interest margin
that the issuer has as an incentive
for bringing more people on the platform.
I would like to see more variety in stablecoins.
And I think we're going to end up seeing that,
although the transition's going to take a little bit of time
and there's going to be competitive dynamics in it.
'Cause you have a circle and tether of great businesses
and they've done a phenomenal job with distribution.
The question would be like,
are they going to end up looking like Diners Club
where the Visa is actually a consortium model?
Or are they going to end up looking like
maybe like a JP Morgan check when the real solution
is the American clearing house of checks.
So there's these new systems that we can imagine
that allow for a lot more distribution much more quickly
than having just one or two issuers
run a lot of on-chain money right now.
- So basically the question that you're asking is,
are the current, the status quo
when it comes to stablecoins,
is that what the technology is going to look like
moving forward?
You mentioned Diners Club,
that was sort of like the proto credit card
before credit cards.
And then the Bank of America card came
and you could use it not just at like a few restaurants,
you could use it all at a whole bunch of merchants.
And then that's sort of the way the industry shifted
was toward this much more generalizable, useful product.
- That's right.
That's exactly what I'm getting at.
I mean, the Diners Club made relationships
with a bunch of basically New York LA restaurants
and said like, charges card, we'll pay back,
he'll be good, Bank of America card launched
in a kind of Sacramento area, I think.
- Fresno was the first drop.
It's kind of the origin story of the air drop by the way,
which is a hilarious little detail.
We've got a good podcast on that actually
all about air drops people can tune into.
- But then it became a consortium
where a lot of people were incentivized
to grow the network.
And I think we probably need that.
I think we probably need to share the incentives
that grow adoption and grow distribution.
And we can't just have Diners Club
or one service provider attempt to go it alone.
We wanna create a credibly neutral network
that's gonna require sharing incentives.
My question here is, you know,
tether and circle, they dominate stablecoins today.
Are they basically going to be Visa MasterCard,
you know, Coke and Pepsi, Uber and Lyft,
or is there gonna be a proliferation
of other options and alternatives?
- Okay, so this is actually the timing on that.
It's perfect.
I don't know when this podcast is gonna come out,
but Circle announced the payment network,
MasterCard announced Deep Stablecoin integration,
and Visa has announced a stablecoin payment product also.
And so the three big incumbents
just fighting to preserve their position in the market.
Part of why I like investing in this category
is because the future's not clear yet.
It could go any way.
The only thing I feel confident in
is that in order to get widespread adoption,
we're gonna have to incentivize distribution.
And so specifically what that means is
Circle or Tether or MasterCard or Visa
is gonna have to open up their pocketbook
and share some of the money they're making
for managing these payments.
I think we shouldn't be deceived.
Like we can't allow a centralized institution
to open up their pocketbook
and then close the door later.
We don't wanna get into a situation
where we're in an extractive network again.
And so the best possible outcome in my mind
is a competitive marketplace built
on top of incredibly neutral decentralized global network
on top of a blockchain.
And I think we're gonna get there,
but the history has not even written
and we're gonna continue to make investments
to help us get into that future as much as we can.
'Cause we think that's sort of the way
that leads to the most prosperity for everyone.
- Sam, from what you're describing,
it sounds like if you wanna understand
how things are going to unfold,
how this industry is going to evolve,
it helps to think about crypto speedrunning
the history of finance.
And so if you wanna understand how it's gonna play out,
look to how finance unfolded.
- I think that's a reasonable thing to say.
But there is a core change here,
which is that we spent 50 years
on top of a legacy technology payment stack
that was actually holding entrepreneurs back.
And so when we look at the next generation
sort of payments products,
they can get much more creative than the last generation.
And so it's not just that we're gonna speedrun
banking history, but we're gonna unlock
very large new opportunities.
So there's products that you never would have attempted
because they would have been too complicated to do before.
Streaming payments is one.
Let's say I pay my electricity at the end of the month.
Could I be paying them on a day-by-day basis?
People have tried it, but the structural costs
were pretty high, the program ability
of legacy payment rails was pretty low.
Well, now you could build a streaming payment product
where you're sending payment as you use something
pretty trivially.
And the benefit is significant.
It might not have been worth the cost before
because it was so complicated
and so expensive to run existing payment rails,
but now you could build that business pretty easily
and people are going to do that.
I mean, electricity companies want to be paid more quickly
and users want lower fees, which they can do
because they're not taking out a loan
from the electricity company.
It's sort of a weird setup that you are getting
a 60-day loan for electrical power in your house.
And there's other things we've got
at Portfolio Company, Blackbird,
they're doing integrated payments
and rewards for restaurants.
Well, there's kind of a reason why
there wasn't a restaurant rewards product
that also handled payments.
The TAM was always large, but the cost to build it
meant that it would be hard to get off the ground.
And look, that's now possible.
And that's because payments are getting a lot cheaper.
You can track loyalty points on chain as well.
You can track restaurant information on chain.
Restaurants aren't scared.
The Blackbird is going to aggregate
and squeeze them because they're on
incredibly neutral decentralized blockchains.
We see it also with agent to agent payments.
Why would the large AI companies
allow just one centralized entity
to run all of the agent to agent transactions?
No, they want it to be on incredibly neutral rails.
And so there's a very long list of things
that only become possible now
that we've got stablecoin payments
and we've got this incredibly neutral infrastructure
to build additional products on top of.
And the whole thing's going to work in tandem
as we grow the TAM of the payments industry.
- That's a really great point
that as much as stablecoins represent an evolution
of progress in the financial system,
they also represent a step change.
We're actually entering this new regime
where things that were once not possible now become possible.
And some of your examples like the confluence
of how stablecoins and crypto might coincide
with AI agent payments.
That's one really great example of the kind of thing
that you maybe could not have prior to this development.
- Yeah, we reached parity.
Steelcoins are as good as traditional payrolls.
Next up is copy table stakes functionality.
And then after that,
we're going to enjoy the benefit of a step change forward
in what entrepreneurs can build on top of stablecoins.
And it's going to touch every industry.
- Looking forward to seeing what people cook up.
You guys, thank you for listeners out there.
If you would like to learn more about this,
check out a16zcrypto.com.
Sam and Chris have written some really great pieces
about stablecoins.
Sam's written about how stablecoins
are going to eat the payments industry
and also how you can look toward the history
of the US banking system
to understand how stablecoins are going to unfold.
And Chris, you've written a great piece
on how stablecoins are payments without intermediaries.
Thank you guys both for coming on the show
and talking about stablecoins.
- Great job, thank you both.
(upbeat music)